[
    {
        "question": "How do subsonic and supersonic fanno flows in long pipes react differently?",
        "answer": "As the viscous flow moves down the pipe, the effective flow area decreases due to friction. This acts as a subsonic nozzle, increasing the velocity of the flow. For supersonic flow, it acts as a diffuser, reducing the velocity of the flow."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the relationship between the mach angle and the wave angle for an oblique shock?",
        "answer": "The wave angle is greater than the mach angle unless the wedge angle is very near 0."
    },
    {
        "question": "How can a T-S diagram show that heat addition is dependent on path, not state?",
        "answer": "The area between reverisble curves in a T-S diagram is equal to heat addition in a cyclic process. There are multiple paths that a process can take between states on the diagram, so therefore heat is dependent on path."
    },
    {
        "question": "How do changes in entropy occur in a process?",
        "answer": "Changes in entropy are due to addition or subtraction of heat with respect to tempurature, or becuase of irreversibilities in the process. Irreversibilities can arise from turbulent flow, unrestrained expansion of a gas, and heat transfer losses."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the difference in measurement between a pressure tube facing a flow and one normal to it?",
        "answer": "A normal tube measures the full velocity of the flow, and hence, the pressure. A tube that faces the flow causes the flow to stagnate, measuring 0 velocity and a pressure of (pressure + 1/2*density*(true velocity)^2)."
    },
    {
        "question": "How would the mach number of a jet flying at the same velocity vary with differing tempuratures?",
        "answer": "The mach number would be lower with a lower tempurature, becuase mach number is inversely related to the square root of tempurature."
    },
    {
        "question": "How can one derive a relation between mach numbers across a shock?",
        "answer": "Multiplying isentropic conservation of energy with continuity and dividing it by momentum relates the mach numbers across a shock. There are two solutions, one where there is a shock, and one where the mach number stays the same and ther is no shock."
    },
    {
        "question": "What differentiates a system from a control volume?",
        "answer": "In a system, the mass remains constant and mass connot cross the system boundary, but energy in the form of work amd heat can, and the boundary can change in size. A control volume has the same properties as a system, but mass can flow through the volume with equal inlet and outlet massflows. Additionally, control volumes cannot change size."
    },
    {
        "question": "What forces acting on a fluid blob do the navier-stokes equations consider?",
        "answer": "The navier stokes equations consider the pressure forces acting on each face of a blob, as well as shear forces from the fluid viscosity."
    },
    {
        "question": "A combustion chamber has an ablative liner, and the volume increases during the burn. If the initial stagnation pressure is 300 psi, and the pressure at the throat is 100psi, how much can the volume of the chamber increase and still remained choked? Assume a perfect gas with gamma of 1.4.",
        "answer": {
            "code": "\n            import numpy as np\n\n            p01 = 300 # initial stagnation pressure (psi)\n            pt = 100 # throat static pressure (psi)\n            # to stay choked, pt/p0 must be < 0.528\n\n            p02 = pt / 0.528 # min choked stagnation pressure (psi)\n\n            dv = p01/p02 # change in volume ratio\n\n            print("The volume can increase by a maximum of:", dv, "x while remaining choked")\n\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the the fact that exit static pressure must be less than 0.528 * (upstream stagnation pressure). Since the amount of gas in the chmaber stays constant. Pressure inversely decreases with an increase in volume. Therefore maximum volume increase can be calculated as the point when chamber stagnation pressure is equal to exit static pressure / 0.528."

        }
    },
    {
        "question": "Calculate the efficiency of a reverisble cyclic heat engine between a hot and cold resovoir. The hot resovoir has a temp of 300C, and the cold has a temp of 5C.",
        "answer": {
            "code": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1 = 300 + 273.15 # convert to kelvin\nT2 = 5 + 273.15 # convert to kelvin\nnu = 1 - T2/T1 # caclulate efficiency for a reversible process\nprint("Efficiency: ", nu)\n",
            "explanation": "This code calculates efficiency for a reverisble process using the equation nu = 1 - (T2/T1), where nu represents efficiency, T1 represents the tempurature of the hot resovoir, and T2 represents the tempurature of the cold resovoir."
        }
    },
    {
        "question": "Calculate the static pressure and tempurature downstream of shock that occurs in a flow with a mach number of 2. The upstream static pressure is 4 bar, and the upstream static tempurature is 400K. Assume the fluid to be air, and gamma to be 1.4.",
        "answer": {
            "code": "\n            import numpy as np\n\n            p1 = 4 # initial static pressure\n            T1 = 400 # initial static tempurature\n            gamma = 1.4 # cp/cv ratio for air\n            M1 = 2 # initial mach number\n            p2 = p1*((2 * gamma * M1**2) / (gamma + 1) - (gamma -1) / (gamma + 1))\n            T2 = T1*(1 + (gamma - 1)/2 * M1**2) * ((2 * gamma) / (gamma - 1) * M1**2 - 1) / ((gamma + 1)**2 / (2 * (gamma - 1)) * M1**2)\n            print("Downstream static pressure: ", p2, "bar.", " Downstream static temp: ", T2, "K.")            \n            ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the static pressture and tempurature ratios downstream of a shock in a mach 2 flow using the shock relations. It multiplies these ratios by the inital pressure and tempurature to get the final values. Friction is assumed to be negligible."
        }
    },
    {
        "question": "An incompressible flow of water (rho = 1000kg/m^3) enters a horizontal pipe at a 45 degree angle with respect to the normal of the entrance. The inlet areat is 1 m^2. The velocity of the flow is 10 m/s. Calculate the exit massflow out of the pipe.",
        "answer": {
            "code": "\n            import numpy as np\n            v = 10 # total flow velocity (m/s)\n            rho = 1000 # density of water (kg/m*3)\n            A = 1 # area of inlet (m^2)\n            vx = v * np.sin(np.pi/4) # obtain x component of flow, pi/4 radians= 45 degrees\n            print(vx)\n            mdot1 = rho * A * vx # calculate massflow into the pipe (kg/s)\n            mdot2 = mdot1 # apply continuity to show massflow in = massflow out\n            print("Massflow out: ", mdot2, "kg/s")\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the x component of the flow velocity using trigonometry. Then it applies the massflow equation: mdot = rho*A*v to find the inlet velocity. From continuity, this value is the same as the exit massflow."
        }
    },
    {
        "question": "Calculate the pressure in an isentropic polytropic process with a polytropic constant of 2 and a volume of 2 L. Assume gamma is 1.4.",
        "answer": {
            "code": "\n            import numpy as np\n            gamma = 1.4 # cp/cv\n            C = 2 # polytropic constant (bar * L)\n            n = gamma # polytropic index for a isentropic process\n            V = 2 # volume in litres\n            p = C / (V**n) # apply the equation for a polytropic process (bar)\n            print("Pressure: ", p, " bar.") \n            ",
            "explanation": "This code utlized the polytropic process equation (pV^n = C) for an isentrpoic process n = gamma. It solves the equation for p (pressure)."
        }
    },
    {
        "question": "Cacluate the specific heat transferred to a perfect gas flow with an inlet velocity of 100m/s and an exit velocity of  250 m/s and a change in tempuratre across the control volume of 50K. Assume a cp = 1006 kJ/kg*K and that there is no work.",
        "answer": {
            "code": "\n            import numpy as np\n\n# change in potential engery is negligible\ndT = 50 # temp (K)\nv1 = 100 # inlet velocity (m/s)\nv2 = 250 # outlet velocity (m/s)\ncp = 1006 # kJ/kg*K\n\n# apply steady flow energy equation\nq = cp * dT + (v2**2)/2 - (v1**2)/2 # calculate q (kJ/kg)\nprint("Specific heat transfer: ", q, " kJ/kg.")\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the specific steady flow energy to calculate specific heat transfer in the abscence of work. It uses the formula dh = cp * dT to relate tempurature difference in a perfect gas to enthalpy difference, where dh is  change in enthalpy, dT is change in tempurature, and cp is specific heat capacity. It plugs the results into the SFEE.",
            "references": [
                "https://ocw.mit.edu/ans7870/16/16.unified/thermoF03/chapter_6.htm"
            ]
        }
    },
    {
        "question": "Find the cv for an incompressible perfect gas in which the specific entropy change in reversible process is 20 kJ/kg, with an initial tempurature of 400K and a change in tempurature of 46C. ",
        "answer": {
            "code": "\n            import numpy as np\n\n            ds = 20 # change in entropy (kJ/kg)\n            dT = 46 # change in tempurature (K)\n            T1 = 400 # initial tempurature (K)\n\n            # apply Tds to solve for cv\n            cv = ds / np.log((T1 + dT) / T1) # kJ / kg * K\n            print("The cv is: ", cv, " kJ / kg * K")\n\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the Tds equation ds = cv*ln(T2/T1) + R*ln(rho1/rho2) to solve for cv. Since the fluid is incompressible, the R term is 0, and cv can be solved for by dividing the change in entropy (ds) by the natural log of the tempurature ratio (T2/T1). "
        }
    }

]